Peter Doub papers, 1829-1868
Emory University
Peter Doub papers, 1829-1868
Doub, Peter, 1796-1869.
Manuscript Collection No. 24
2 linear ft. (4 boxes) and 3 oversized papers (OP)
Articles, sermons, letters, reports, minutes, essays and a photocopy of the diary of Methodist clergyman Peter Doub.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Gift.
Restrictions on Access
Unrestricted access.
Biographical Note
Peter Doub, Methodist clergyman, was born March 12, 1786, in Stokes (now Forsythe) County, North Carolina, and died August 24, 1869, in Greensboro, North Carolina. He served the Methodist Episcopal Church as a circuit rider and itinerant minister for twenty-one years; he was a professor of Biblical literature for three years and a temperance lecturer for one year. Doub was one of three founders of Greensboro Female College. Articles written by him were published in the North Carolina Christian Advocate and other periodicals.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of articles, sermons, letters, reports, minutes, essays, diaries, and lists of Peter Doub from 1796-1869. Portions of the collection, such as the diary, are photocopies of original materials.
Topics of the materials include temperance, the Methodist Episcopal Church, the conflict of the Methodist Church with the Presbyterian Church in Virginia, biblical literature, slavery, baptism, and confirmation. Minutes are from North Carolina Quarterly Conference (1844-1845) and the Methodist General Conference (1828; 1846). There are also extracts from the journals of Reverend James Meacham and a photocopy of Doub's diary.
Arrangement Note
Arranged by record type.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Andrew, James O. (James Osgood), 1794-1871.; Meacham, James--Diaries.
Corporate Names
Methodist Episcopal Church--History.; Methodist Episcopal Church. General Conference.; Methodist Episcopal Church. Conferences. North Carolina.; Methodist Episcopal Church, South--History.
Topical Terms
Baptism.; Clergymen--Diaries.; Clergymen as authors.; Clergymen's writings.; Methodist Church--Clergy.; Methodist Church--Virginia.; Presbyterian Church--Virginia.; Religious education.; Sermons, American.; Slavery and the church.; Temperance and religion.
Geographic Names
North Carolina--Religion.
Form/Genre Terms
Diaries.; Conference minutes.; Essays.; Reports.; Sermons.
Occupation
Circuit rider.; Clergy.
Related Materials in Other Repositories
The original diary and other related collections are in the possession of Duke University Library, Durham, North Carolina.
Container List
- Articles
- Episcopacy, Church, powers of clergy, etc. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Greensborough Patriot (Box 1, Folder 2)
- North Carolina Christian Advocate, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- North Carolina Christian Advocate, 1857-1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Richmond Christian Advocate, 1836 (Box OP1)
- Spirit of the Age (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Various publications, September 29, 1851-October 22, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Virginia Conference Sentinel (Box OP2)
- Church records
- Minutes, General Conference, May 1828 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Notes and minutes: North Carolina Conference, 1843-1845 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Minutes--containing resolution relative to deposing Bishop Andrew on grounds of slaveholding (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Plans for unifying Methodist Episcopal Church, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letters, reviews and lists of North Carolina ministers (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Books of examination questions (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Writings, sermons
- Communion (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Confirmation, Institutions of Christianity (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Infant baptism, Unity of the Church, Religious education, Episcopacy (Box OP3)
- Episcopacy (Box 1, Folder 15)
- The Ministry (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Sin and its consequences; Episcopacy (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Temperance and replies to Holdenism (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Outlines, miscellaneous; obituaries (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Outlines, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Outlines, miscellaneous; poems on Calvinism (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Outlines, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Writings, by subject
- "Brother Drake" and "Infant Baptism Considered" (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Notes and treatises on baptism (one is 50 pages) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Lectures and essays on baptism (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Doctrine and sermon on baptismal regeneration (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Infant Baptism," 53 pages (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Biblical literature, Course outline and lectures, Trinity College, 1867-1868 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Biblical literature, questions on lectures (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Essay: Faith is not to be kept with heretics (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Slavery (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Addresses delivered before the North Carolina. Sons of Temperance, 1852 [4] (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Temperance (Box 2, Folder 11)
- An Essay on the Evils of Intemperance (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Essay on Psalms 45:4-5 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Scripture passages and comments (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Scripture passages and comments (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Scripture passages and comments (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Scripture passages and comments (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Scripture passages and comments (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Essays, Truth asserted and error detected; truth vindicated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Writings, other
- Miscellaneous discourses and essays (including review of controversy between Methodists and Presbyterians in Central Virginia, and a sermon at funeral of Gaston Egbert Brown) (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous sermons and essays (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous writings and fragments (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous writings: poems, prayers, memoirs, etc. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- "Strictures on the Work of a Layman" entitled "The Suffering Christ"--last pages contain a list of "monies received from preachers in payment of my salary for 1867" (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Memorandum book, contains: a. a review of George W. Gumby’s work on Universalism; b. examination of all Biblical passages mentioning wine; c. Expense account--a very few entries, 1865, 1866 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Peter Doub, January 22, 183?, hardbound book, includes 2 articles on baptism; outline laid in on Lay Representation (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Journals of Rev. James Meacham, extracts (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Review of a discourse delivered in the Baptist Church at Raleigh, during the session of the Legislature, November 30, 1829. By Rev. William W. Hill, the substance of which discourse, he subsequently delivered in the town of Greensboro, Guilford County, North Carolina on Sunday the 27th of June 1830 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Notebook, "Instructions in the Hebrew Language" (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Doub diary [Photocopy - original at Duke University] (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Ephemera
- Peter Doub's pouch (Box 4, Folder 9)